Guide to the Carl Menger Papers, 1857-1985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Notes on Methodology (Box 13)
  - Notes on philosophical topics, c. 1910s, (3 folders) (Box 19)
  - Notes on philosophical topics, c. 1910s (Box 20)
- Correspondence (Box 20)
  Contains letters to Carl Menger, predominantly from economist colleagues, especially E. Böhm-Bawerk, J. Conrad, E. Philippovich, E. Sax, and F. Wieser, concerning professional matters. Menger's drafts are in the minority; most seem to be to E. Böhm-Bawerk. Several letters concern early professional matters, Menger's association with Rudolf, the crown prince of Austria, and his appointment at the University of Vienna. The series also includes letters to Karl Menger from economists such as F. Hayek. L. Mises, O. Morgenstern, R. Schuller, J. Schumpeter, K. Wicksell, and R. Zuckerkandl. They date primarily from the 1920s and 1930s, with a few dating from the 1960s to the mid-1980s. Matters covered include Karl Menger's publication of the second edition of his father's Grundsätze and his later work on the Austrian School.
  - Carl Menger, 1863-1884 (Box 20)
  - Carl Menger, 1885-1888 (Box 20)
  - Carl Menger, 1889-1920 and undated (Box 20)
  - Karl Menger, 1914-1985 and undated (Box 20)
  - Anton Menger, 19?? (Box 20)
- Biographical Materials (Box 20)
  Contains a biographical sketch by F. Hayek which appeared in volume one of the Collected Works of Carl Menger (Series of Reprints of Scarce Tracts in Economic and Political Science, London School of Economics and Political Science, 1934) and various lists for a curriculum vitae of Menger. A valuable but short (48 leaves) diary which Menger kept from l875 to 1893/4 lists major events since his birth in 1840, but deals primarily with Menger's health, his appointments as a journalist, employment in the press section of the Austrian prime minister's office, his association with Crown Prince Rudolf, university politics, and academic research. A folder contains notices of celebrations for Menger's seventieth and seventy-fifth birthdays, and obituaries. There is one undated postcard/photograph of Menger and a friend fishing.
  - Diary, 1875-1894 (with information from 1840) (Box 21)
  - Diary transcriptions and notes on Carl Menger's life by Karl Menger, 12 pp. and 1 blue notebook (Box 21)
  - Honors: (Box 21)
    - 1. Iron Cross, III class, 1876 (Box 21)
    - 2. "Correspondant," Institut de France, 1894;2 letters of congratulation (Box 21)
    - 3. "Correspondant," La Société de statistique de France, 1897 (Box 21)
    - 4. Certificate of Admission, Regia Lynceorum Academia, 1899 (Box 21)
    - 5. Honorary president for 1901, Institut international de Sociologie, 1900 (Box 21)
    - 6. Requests for C. Menger to accept other positions; 1 envelope, 2 sheets (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous information, dates, etc. (Box 21)
  - News Clippings, Articles in honor of Menger's 60th, 70th and 75th birthday, his retirement (1903), and on the occasion of his death (Box 21)
  - Commemoration of Menger on his 70th birthday (R. Zuckerkandl) (Box 21)
  - Introduction for the Collected Works of Carl Menger (London School of Economics and Political Science) by F. Hayek (Box 21)
  - Photographs: (Box 21)
    - 1. Carl Menger? (Box 21)
    - 2. "Daughter of Dr. Perin" 1911 (Box 21)
    - 3. Carl Menger and friend, undated (Box 21)
- Related Family Materials (Box 21)
  Contains Railways and Financial Institutions, possibly associated with one of the Mengers; a tribute to Anton Menger by K. Grandüberg; various articles by Anton Menger; a diary, 1861-70, and obituaries of Max Menger; an article by Karl Menger.
  - Menger (?): Railways and Financial Institutions (Box 22)
  - Anton Menger: Sein Leben und Lebenswerk (K. Grünberg); Das Recht auf den vollen Arbeitsertrag; Neue Sittenlehre; Ueber die sozialen Aufgaben der Rechtswissenschaft (Box 22)
  - Anton Menger: Volkspolitik (Box 22)
  - Anton Menger (?): Rede beim Antritte des Rectorats, 1874 (Box 22)
  - Max Menger: Diary, 1861-1870 (Box 22)
  - Max Menger: Die Reform der directen Steuern in Oesterreich (Box 22)
  - Max Menger: Obituaries (Box 22)
  - Karl Menger: The Logic of the Laws of Return (reprint) (Box 23)
  - Karl Menger: Articles he collected? (Box 23)
    - 1. Italien...Flugmalerei (R. Vasari) (Box 23)
    - 2. On Equilibrium in Graham's Model of World Trade... (L. McKenzie) (Box 23)
    - 3. Pluralist Approach to the Philosophy of History (K. Popper) (Box 23)
    - 4. Educational Theatre and UNESCO (H. Schnitzler) (Box 23)
    - 5. Introduction, Activity Analysis of Production and Allocation (by Karl Popper) (Box 23)
    - 6. Derivation of Bond Pricing Formula (Box 23)
  - Karl Menger: Recht und Logik (F. Paradies) (Box 23)
  - Karl Menger: Miscellaneous News Clippings (Box 23)
  - Karl Menger: Miscellaneous recollections, 1 partial page. (Box 23)
- Miscellaneous (Box 23)
  Includes notes; bibliographical references on topics other than economics or methodology; and partial catalog of Carl Menger's library arranged alphabetically.
  - Bill for Neue Freie Presse, 1909 (Box 23)
  - Early Writings (Box 23)
  - Writings (Box 23)
  - Entwurf der Statuten für die Redehalle (Box 23)
  - Printed description of university life, after 1903 (Box 23)
  - Notes on Prague Univ. Student Associations (Box 23)
  - Bibliographical References (Box 23)
  - Catalog of Carl Menger's Library (Box 23)
  - List of materials in the Vienna Univ. Library not in Menger's personal library, 1869 (Box 23)
  - "Von alten Büchern. Antiquarische Bücher und Antiquare" (Box 23)
  - Notes on Austrian Politics by Crown Prince Rudolf (Box 23)
  - Notes on Progressive Income Tax (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Carl Menger and Karl Menger (?) (Box 23)
  - "Sonnenfels" (Box 23)
- Printed Matter (Box 23)
  Includes books and articles by Menger, many with his annotations; some proofs of items in press; reviews of Menger's works; articles sent to him by other authors; clippings on the Austrian university students' uprisings; and news clippings concerning articles by Menger and others.
  - News Clippings: Reviews by Carl Menger (Box 24)
  - News Clippings: Articles by Carl Menger (Box 24)
  - News Clippings: Reviews of Carl Manger's Works (Box 24)
  - News Clipping Copies: Reviews Concerning Menger (Box 24)
  - News Clippings: Articles by Carl Menger on universities and their reform (Box 24)
  - News Clippings: Miscellaneous (Box 24)
  - News Clippings: Reviews of Grundsätze, 2nd ed. (Box 24)
  - Grundsätze, copies 1 and 2, (2 folders) (Box 24)
  - Grundsätze, unnumbered copy (Box 24)
  - Grundsätze, unnumbered copy (Box 25)
  - Grundsätze, 2nd ed., Handexemplar (Box 25)
  - Grundsätze, 2nd ed., galley proofs for pp. 87-91, 99-101 (Box 25)
  - Untersuchungen with Menger's annotations (Box 25)
  - Untersuchungen, (2 folders) (Box 25)
  - Untersuchungen, bound in signatures with blank leaves. Used by F. Hayek in preparing a 2nd ed., nos. I-II, 1-10, 12-14 (Box 25)
  - Untersuchungen, bound in signatures with blank leaves. Used by F. Hayek in preparing a 2nd ed., nos. 15-19 (Box 26)
  - Irrthümer des Historismus with revisions by Karl Menger (Box 26)
  - "Zur Kritik der Politischen Oekonomie," 2 copies (Box 26)
  - "Zur Theorie des Kapitals," 2 copies in German; 1 translation in French (Box 26)
  - "Grundzüge einer Klassifikation der Wirtschaftswissenchaften" (Box 26)
  - On the Origin of Money (Box 26)
  - Ein Gesetz gegen Kartelle (Box 26)
  - Geld, 1900 (2nd ed. of Handwörterbuch,), 3 copies (Box 26)
  - Geld, 1909 (3rd ed. of Handwörterbuch), 6 copies (Box 26)
  - Geld, 1909 (3rd ed. of Handwörterbuch), 5 copies (Box 26)
  - Articles on Currency Reform: (Box 26)
    - 1. Beiträge zur Währungsfrage... (Box 26)
    - 2. Das Goldagio und der heutige Stand der Valutareform (Box 26)
    - 3. Der Uebergang zur Goldwährung (Box 26)
    - 4. Die Valutaregulierung in Oesterreich-Ungarn (incomplete) (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous works not by Menger (Box 26)
    - 1. Das Selbstbewusstsein (T. Lipps) (incomplete) (Box 26)
    - 2. On geistige Arbeit (incomplete) (Box 26)
  - Works by Colleagues: (Box 26)
    - 1. Zins (Böhm-Bawerk) (Box 26)
    - 2. Preis (Zuckerkandl) (Box 26)
    - 3. Sostarnyia chasti i metody politicheskoi ekonomii (A. A. Isaeva) (Box 26)
  - Articles relating to Carl Menger and the Austrian School: (Box 26)
    - 1. Fundamentals of Austrian Economics (T. C. Taylor) (Box 26)
    - 2. Menger on Ricardo (K. Yagi) (Box 26)
    - 3. Böhm-Bawerk's First Interest Theory (K. Yagi) (Box 26)
    - 4. Review of Carl Menger and the Austrian School of Economics (Jaffé) (Box 26)
  - Articles by Karl Menger: (Box 26)
    - 1. Austrian Marginalism and Mathematical Economics (galley proofs; 1 English copy; 1 German copy; 1 German summary) (Box 26)
    - 2. Program from One Hundred Years of Carl Menger's 'Grundsätze der Volkswirtschaftslehre,' 2 copies (Box 26)
- Oversize Material (Box 26)
  - Printed Matter: Die Schillerzeit (contribution by Menger, among others, to commemoration of Schiller, 1905) (Box Sec. A OV12)
  - Printed Matter: Review of Böhm-Bawerk's Positive Theorie des Kapitals (Box Sec. A OV12)
  - Biographical Materials: Honors. Election to Societas Regia Edinensis, 1895. (Box Sec. A OV12)
  - Biographical Materials: Application for Habilitation, 1871 (Box Sec. A OV12)
  - Miscellaneous: Notes on Austrian Student Rising (Box Sec. A OV12)